John A. J. Creswell Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John A. J. Creswell Papers 1819-1885 (bulk 1862-1885)
MSS17236
Creswell, John A. J. (John Angel James), 1828-1891
6,000 items
21 containers plus one oversize
8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, congressman, senator, and postmaster general. General correspondence, letterbooks, account books, and scrapbooks concerning Creswell’s law practice and political career in Maryland, his duties as adjutant general of Maryland, the military draft during the Civil War, the Maryland Constitutional Convention of 1867, and American claims regarding the Alabama.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carroll, Thomas King, 1793-1873--Correspondence.; Childs, George William, 1829-1894--Correspondence.; Creswell, John A. J., 1828-1891.; Davis, Henry Winter, 1817-1865--Correspondence.; Duncan, Levi--Correspondence.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885--Correspondence.; Hawley, Joseph R. (Joseph Roswell), 1826-1905--Correspondence.; Hicks, Thomas Holliday, 1798-1865--Correspondence.; Johnson, Reverdy, 1796-1876--Correspondence.; Morgan, Edwin D. (Edwin Denison), 1811-1883--Correspondence.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912--Correspondence.; Townsend, George Alfred, 1841-1914--Correspondence.; Washburne, E. B. (Elihu Benjamin), 1816-1887--Correspondence.
Organizations
Alabama (Screw sloop); Maryland. Adjutant General.; Maryland. Constitutional Convention (1867)
Subjects
Alabama claims.; Constitutional conventions--Maryland.; Draft--United States.; Maryland--Politics and government.; Patronage, Political.; Practice of law--Maryland.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Claims.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Lawyers.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Maryland.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Maryland.
Provenance
The papers of John A. J. Creswell, lawyer, congressman, senator, and postmaster general, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1926 and 1939.
Access and Restrictions
The John A. J. Creswell Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1828, Nov. 18 Born, Port Deposit, Md.
1848 Graduated, Dickinson College, Carlisle, Pa.
1850 Began law practice, Elkton, Md.
1856 Delegate to the Democratic national convention
1861 Member, Maryland House of Delegates Affiliated with the Republican party
1862 1863 Adjutant general of Maryland
1863 1865 Member, United States House of Representatives
1865 1867 Member, United States Senate
1869 1874 Postmaster general
1874 1876 Counsel, Alabama Claims Commission
1876 Resumed law practice
1891, Dec. 23 Died near Elkton, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Angel James Creswell (1828-1891) span the years 1819-1885, with the bulk of the material dated 1862-1885. A government official, supporter of Abraham Lincoln, and abolitionist, Creswell changed his name from John Andrew Jackson Creswell to John Angel James Creswell after being elected to the House of Representatives as a Republican in 1861 in order to disassociate himself from Democrat Andrew Jackson. His papers consist of general correspondence, letterbooks, account books, and scrapbooks.
The general correspondence, chiefly 1862-1865, consists mainly of bound volumes of letters to Creswell concerning his law practice, business, Maryland politics, patronage, his duties as adjutant general of Maryland, the military draft during the Civil War, and the Maryland Constitutional Convention of 1867. The letterbooks, 1882-1885, pertain to American interests presented to the United States Court of Commissioners of Alabama Claims.
Correspondents include Thomas King Carroll, George William Childs, Henry Winter Davis, Levi Duncan, Ulysses S. Grant, Joseph R. Hawley, Thomas Holliday Hicks, Reverdy Johnson, Edwin D. Morgan, Whitelaw Reid, George Alfred Townsend, and E. B. Washburne.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - Bound (Box 1)
    - 1819, Aug. 1-1862, June 23 (Box 1)
    - 1862, June 27-1863, Nov. 11 (Box 2)
    - 1863, Nov. 13-Dec. 12 (Box 3)
    - 1863, Dec. 17-1864, Jan. 23 (Box 4)
    - 1864 (Box 5)
      - Jan. 24-Feb. 16 (Box 5)
      - Feb. 17-Mar. 10 (Box 6)
      - Mar. 11-Apr. 9 (Box 7)
      - Apr. 11-May 25 (Box 8)
      - May 26-Oct. 7 (Box 9)
      - Oct. 9-Dec. 6 (Box 10)
    - 1864, Dec. 7-1865, Jan. 15 (Box 11)
    - 1865 (Box 12)
      - Jan. 16-Feb. 27 (Box 12)
      - Mar. 2-June 12 (Box 13)
      - June 13-Aug. 5 (Box 14)
      - Aug. 7-Oct. 6 (Box 15)
      - Oct. 7-Dec. 13 (Box 16)
    - 1865, Dec. 14-1887, Aug. 22, undated (Box 17)
  - Unbound, 1869-1874, 1880-1884 (Box 18)
- Letterbooks, Alabama claims (Box 18)
  - 1882, Aug. 31-1883, July 2, (3 vols.) (Box 18)
  - 1883, July 2-1885, Feb. 25, (4 vols.) (Box 19)
  - 1885, Feb. 25-Nov. 25, (4 vols.) (Box 20)
- Miscellany (Box 21)
  - Account books, 1848-1869, 1884, (2 vols.) (Box 21)
  - Notebook, 1884-1885 (Box 21)
  - Scrapbooks, 1872-1885 See Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 21)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbooks (Container 21) (Box OV 1)
    - 1872-1882 (Box OV 1)
    - 1882-1885 (Box OV 1)